hello everyone and welcome back to
active inference insights I am your host
Daris parvy Wayne and today I'm thrilled
to be speaking with Connor Hines Connor
is a PhD student although he just told
me he just finished his PhD at the max
plank Institute of animal behavior as
well as a researcher at versus AI his
work focuses on the apparent Theology of
complex systems and especially how they
can be described as conducting
variational basian inference over their
environment
thus Connor leans heavily on active
infont and the free energy principle in
his analysis Collective Behavioral
Systems and so he is the perfect guest
for today's episode Connor Thank you so
much for being here I'm super excited to
learn from you um I need to put my
technical hat on because your papers are
are technical um but I think there's a
lot that non-technical audiences will be
able to get out of them and I want to
start having me no no it's genuinely
it's absolutely my pleasure um I feel
like psychology or cognitive science
likes taking the unit of analysis as the
individual and then saying okay how can
we extrapolate from the individual to
describe group
dynamics so I wanted to start very
broadly with a kind of axiomatic
question about when you uh study
Collective systems is there a difference
between Collective behavior in and of
itself like what you talk about in terms
of collective behavior and then the
behavior of an aggregation of
individuals who we can say belong to a
group so is there something over and
above the behavior of individuals when
we talk about Collective Behavior yeah I
mean this is this question is is one of
the motivations for why ended up
studying this and I think it ties into
like what I would say is a larger
unifying theme of complex systems in
general complex system science I think
if you could like sum up sum it up in
one phrase would be more is
different the whole is greater or
different than the sum of its parts um
and that is really evident I think in
the study Collective Behavior so yeah I
I would say that there's something
absolutely different about kind of
blurring your eyes so to speak on the
individual components of a system and
treating the system as a thing as an
emergent thing and there's a lot of
theories about whether that's like an
Epi phenomenal thing is that just
something that exists on on a
descriptive level or does this larger
thing like a flock of birds or a school
of fish or a society or an economy does
it in some way have like causal power
and influence on these like level
individuals but I like the the larger if
the last like whatever 30 years of
complex system science has shown us that
yes there is something qualitatively
different about the bigger picture than
just an aggregation of uh individual
components yeah I think in terms of
let's say sociocultural groups the top-
down influence is quite transparent I
mean in terms of an economy the economy
that you've function in presumably has a
kind of circular causality with the
agents in the economy totally I'm
wondering whether in terms of more
mechanical complex systems um so even in
let's say simulation work is there
something that emerges ontologically in
terms of the actual dynamics of the
group as a whole that can't be reduced
to let's say just like a summation of
those individual behaviors and I guess
in that even if there is can we
distinguish that from top- down
causality so as you say you might have
something which like is ontologically
different you can actually say okay this
is a different phenomenon but where do
you see the top down causality coming in
before we get to let's say languages or
broader cultures or uh economies yeah no
that's a that's a hotly debated topic
effectively so there's a lot of work
that's kind of trying to actually
quantify the amount of top- down
causation that there is because of
course like we can always Define some
set of macroscopic or coar grain
variables from an ensemble of
microscopic variables like say I have a
bunch of particles or a bunch of gas
particles I can take like averages like
and come up with quantities like the
temperature or the average mass or the
average velocity the question is is that
coar grain variable actually doing
anything to that lower level does it
feed back down and um my intuition is
even in simulation yes there is and then
people have tried to Quant quantify this
there's people like um liel Barnett and
uh Neil Seth at Sussex University of
Sussex who have come up with quantities
like dynamical Independence so there's
an idea where these coar grain variables
don't just act as descriptors or
aggregators of lower level constituents
but they end up having their own causal
power and like intuitively when you hear
that it's quite hard to imagine how
that's possible um but it's I think it's
one of the most fascinating and kind of
magical things about complex systems is
that basically these slower like both
like spatially and temporally coar grain
variables end up kind of uh accumulating
a life of their own and they can in fact
influence and in some ways be more
predictive of the lower variables um
than just taking the whole like Ensemble
of lower variables as predictors
themselves um I don't to be quite Frank
although I'm quite confident this exists
I don't have a great intuition for how
that's possible because it kind of flies
in the face of the last you know 200
years of reductionist science which is
basically saying that the only causal
direction is up everything starts like
you know with gluons and quirks and then
you kind of build the universe up from
there but all this research is
suggesting that there is some degree of
downward causal influence and
ontologically it's actually quite
philosophically difficult to like reckon
with that I don't I don't know why that
is yes I mean I wonder whether it's just
a slightly different type of causation
um from the kind of gluons or quarks up
in sense that you know um going all the
way back to Aristotle people talk about
constraint versus causation and it might
be that just C macro systems constrain
the organization of micro system but
yeah it's a massive question and yeah as
you said it's very philosophically rich
I mean strong emergence weak emergence
all of this kind of stuff is exactly
really philosophical excellent um going
to sort of humans or are in silico
simulations of humans or cognitive
agents um when you put when you sort of
run these in silico simulations you
equip you know I read one of your papers
you equip them with social information
right social prior so in one of the your
you had distance to the ne their
neighbors or you would have the rates of
the change of the distance I'm wondering
whether would it be possible you know do
individual agents need to be equipped
with these social priors to become
social agents or is there a way that
actually just by acting and let's say
having a shared goal but without actual
reference to the presence of other
agents we have this kind of gal or we
have this kind of emergence of a overall
pattern yeah definitely I I think so
basically there's different ways you can
effectively introduce correlations or
coupling between agents um the way that
we think I mean there's a lot of
evidence that animals and agents in
society do correlate each other's
activity is through either directly or
indirectly perceiving aspects of the
other like we can see each other um
schooling fish can sense their neighbors
bacteria uh can sense each other in kind
of like all sorts of uh interesting ways
but there's nothing qualitatively saying
that you can't couple um a a system of
particles with some like third qut like
uh driving or common source so for
instance if I have a bunch of um
particles trying to navigate towards a
food source on some like media like
they're all attracted by biochemical
gradients towards a food source of
course that will induce correlations in
their activity so it will seem like
they're all moving as one where as in
fact there's nothing that's actually
letting them sense each other but
they're just some kind of common um
Source that's giving the appearance of
correlated activity and this like is a
very uh this is a classic thing that
comes up in Neuroscience too when we're
looking at large recordings of neurons
often times we're not rec in the whole
brain right we're just looking at some
small subsection of neural activity and
you see all these correlations between
uh neural firing patterns and you say oh
look they're connected people use all
kinds of correlational techniques to
infer the the nature of those
interactions oh this neuron is driving
that neuron but you actually never know
if there's some third um causal driving
force that's actually responsible for
correlating their activity and this is
actually one of the nice things about
studying Collective animal behavior like
in the lab of um Ian cousin where I did
my my PhD they have the ability to kind
of track with High um resolution a bunch
of individuals like every individual in
an ensemble in a collective and they can
even reconstruct kind of to some extent
the visual fields and the sensory fields
of the individuals in the group and in
that way they can kind of decouple these
potentially third correlating or
confounding factors from the actual use
of so social information that the
individuals might be utilizing that's
cool that's interesting um yeah because
I can imagine without that it can be
very confounded and it makes me think to
what degree here is uh Collective
Behavior genuinely advantageous for
these organisms and I guess it comes to
a kind of evolutionary question there is
this evolutionary debate about what you
know what is the what is the transmitted
thing over Epoch is it the actual Gene
the speci collective and so on exactly
you know in some sense if we just say
well there are these collect you know
these aggregations of individuals which
have similar goals and therefore look as
if they are acting in accordance with
one another and obviously when you start
recognizing others well then you have to
start taking them into account your work
have you have you got any intuition as
to whether the presence of others with
shared goals is actually beneficial for
the organism who's pursuing that
individual goal or whether you know it'd
be better if we were all siloed off and
an island onto ourselves yeah yeah
that's a that's like a really perennial
question in the study of in not only
Collective Behavior but like
sociobiology kind of in its original
formulation by like EO Wilson is you
know is there something inherently
advantageous to group living and um if
so it's clearly not a be all end all
because we do have the presence of
species that are like solo Predators
like wild cats right they're they're not
living in herds but then there's other
animals that are actually living in
groups and so there's clearly some
trade-off there so I think one answer
that probably biologists because I have
to admit like I often theorize very you
know high level with Concepts from
physics and Mathematics but there are
clear you know individual Fitness and
more selfish Gene related motivations
for group living like a classic um one
that has been used to motivate flocking
and schooling fish is like predation
risk if you're living in a group you're
basically lowering the chance that any
particular individual gets predated
because and there's also interesting
psychological effects that flocking has
on Predators like there's a crowding
effect so if there's a bunch of
individuals in my visual field it's
harder for me to focus on a single one
that collectively lowers the predation
risk of everyone in that collect yeah
yeah yeah so that's one one answer to
that there's another interesting um
answer which I I I don't know this is
maybe a little controversial and I think
this is where it really ties into the
free energy principle which is once you
have a collective system regard
regardless of whether it's actually
beneficial to the individuals that
partake in it if the system has dynamics
that kind of allow it to survive it's
kind of created now its own selection
pressure on it in of itself so the
system um simply by existing and not
dissipating is kind of like self-
evidencing or selecting itself at
perhaps like a higher dynamical scale
and this is where I think Concepts like
the free energy principle which is
really in the game of defining
why things persist in the first place
and what it means to be a thing um has
something to say about about Collective
Behavior so I would actually argue that
there's certain um kind of group
dynamics that exist sometimes even at
the expense of individual Fitness but
once you've entered into this macro
scale the macro scale is kind of living
and trying to find evidence for its own
existence even if that goes back and
punishes uh the individual actors that
actually originally like Co operated to
create it um that's a little bit more
controversial but I think it's a really
good maybe uh framework for
understanding kind of like maladaptive
group dynamics things like
misinformation or virality social
networks things like that well the
Marxist will be screaming that you've
got a great Theory there of capitalist
you know capitalist
realism yeah that's that's really
interesting I mean I guess as a you know
more philosophical bend on this one
thing well where's the kind ofal of
control here because I think intuitively
we don't think that the group dynamics
have control or agency like the overall
Arc of a culture has the agency of its
constituents
individuals but this idea that there's
like again I think it comes down to a
kind of constraint causality distinction
there are certain things that say that
you can do
within capitalist America versus what
you could do in communist Russia MH and
those actors constraints without there
being some homunculus I mean obviously
there are homunculus in in so far as
there are political figures but no
that's that's a really interesting point
I think also what I've been thinking
about is and this is a even deeper
question is and I'm wondering whether
you have to think about this when you
talk about Collective behavior and
aggregating individuals do you ever
think at what point does one individual
end and what and when does it be when
how can we distinguish one individual
from another and I know that sounds
stupid because like people would just
say well it's the body and and you just
have it you just see them and obviously
when we're talking about high level
evolved systems like the visual system
then it probably is based on you know V1
picking out lines which distinguish
indiv uh you know um individual
organisms I'm curious in terms of the
actual basian mechanics and the free
energy principle is there anything that
gives us individuated thingness Beyond
taking that as a kind of axium like oh
no there it just is a thing that is
self- evidencing no yeah I I don't think
it does I think that's one of the
challenges of maybe what the general
problem would be called is like system
identification or Markov blanket
identification how do I like look at
some high-dimensional system and
actually pick out what are the
individuals or the components of that
system and even within um like bi
biological systems it's often not uh
that clear like you and me might look at
uh
Hill of termites or ants colony of ants
and say okay yeah those individual ants
are the individuals but in a system
where they all share the same genetic
material it becomes a little bit unclear
and and especially when you have these
kind of self- ulating sacrifices for the
good of the collective it's you start
thinking about things like the extended
phenotype like are these individuals
actually individuals or are they kind of
just manifestations of some common gene
pool they're kind of like the the tools
and the fingers that the pool is using
to act in the world um so I don't think
that basing mechanics has any like
strict definition about what a thing has
to be I mean people will disagree with
me on this like for instance the recent
work from um people like Carl friston uh
on on particular things strange kinds
the this line of papers actually makes
particular arguments about what cons
what constitutes a thing and it has to
do with a particular set of dynamical
con straints between the different
subsets of a thing like there's active
States and sensory States and there's
certain conditional Independence
relations that have have to exist um so
so the proposals have been made but I
don't think anything about basy
mechanics actually tells you how to do
the partitioning of the state space it's
like given a state space we can then
start interpreting the Dynamics of that
thing as doing some sort of basian
inference but where the actual State
space comes from that's a much deeper
question that I think is like an active
active area of inquiry that's really
yeah that's fascinating because I guess
one way of doing it would be that you
well you act like scientist in some way
and you go well if these things are
behaving differently let's say you got
two ants that are behaving differently
they're diverging in their movements
then you would say well we can make the
assumption that their active and sensory
states are different their Mark or
blanket is different but if they're
replicating one
another then you know that all even that
uh decomposition of the system in of
sensory States and active States kind of
kind of informs you to say that that's
one overarching thing and again I mean I
like recruiting kind of a philosophical
vagueness here which is that like from a
philosophical perspective it's probably
just an empty question and there is you
know it's it's well what point does a
pile of sand become a heap or you know
and so on and it's it's empty if not if
not interesting and maybe beneficial
when we're talking about well I think
there are phenomenological effects about
you know to what what degree do I
recognize myself as a kind of siloed off
individual versus part of a group and
there are probably very aberant ends to
that Spectrum like social isolation
versus schizophrenia where I'm kind of
melting into the world versus being
completely alone so I think there are
there's import but yeah I recognize that
it's yeah I I do think yeah I I I
totally agree on a philosophical level
it affective there is no hard line in
the same there's not going to be some be
all end all definition effect like event
what will be our deciding factor is the
utility or like I guess more pragmatist
sort of stance is like the partition we
choose for a particular system is it
going to help us do something so for
instance in a lot of my um interest in
Collective animal behavior I I've just
been mesmerized by like videos of
schooling fish right and these schooling
these schools are not like cells in the
sense that you know the the I mean cells
potentially violate this as well but the
position and the role that individuals
play Within the school are not fixed
right so fish can like go to different
sides of the school some fish can kind
of act as the eyes and ears of the
school While others are acting more like
the leaders so you have like spontaneous
change in roles and Leadership and that
already is basically telling you that at
the higher level at least the the kind
of sensory states are not assigned like
unchanging individual identities so
there so already the partition we use if
we want to start studying the the school
as an individual that partition has to
kind of supersede individual identity
has to be some spaciotemporal course
graining of like the movements and
identities of different fish or
particles over time and which partition
we use should be a function of like what
question or what hypothesis we're trying
to answer yeah so it comes down to this
theological or pragmatic
motivation have you got this is seems
like a much more bow question but I'm
just curious because I don't know that
much about Collective behavior and bi
have you got a particular favorite of
collective Behavior you mentioned
schools of fish is there anything else
that kind of stands out as impressive
yeah I so schools of fish is probably my
my top one just because they're visually
so mesmerizing I mean Starling flocks
are are quite interesting as well um
particularly because so it often happens
that in many realistic schooling
scenarios although you'll have three
dimensional schools this is something I
I learned from my my adviser Ian in
practice a lot of the school actually is
happening in two Dimensions so even
threedimensional schools are actually
made up of more like 2D manifolds
whereas if you look at Starling flocks
they have very interesting
three-dimensional structure so you've
probably seen these like um what they
call murmurations like these kind of
shimmering and they almost look like
chaotic like strange attractors the way
F over on themselves and even those have
like quasi two-dimensional structure but
they are they're those two dimensional
planes are moving in 3D space and so
stuff like that is just visually very
interesting and there's a lot of really
interesting um research like trying to
do high resolution recording in 3D of
all the birds in a in a flock and trying
to track them so I think that's a really
a beautiful one but again it comes like
it comes back to your earlier question
is what is the actual function of that
some sometimes these murmurations are
very beautiful and like impressive but
people still don't really know like what
the function of like such crazy displays
of collective coordination are yeah it
bring it it brings to mind what you
mentioned about the fact that there are
this actually conversation I had with KL
because we were right at the you know
the first episode of this podcast we
were talking about what is the
imperative Cole you know originally
spoke about an existential imperative
underlying the free energy principle but
it's a slightly misleading term because
it doesn't say that you know we have to
do anything right I could just
disintegrate right now it's saying that
if I do persist then I look as if I am
doing variational Bas inflence so on so
I said to myself well but is there an
underlying tell us to you know is there
an evolutionary pressure to survive
right this is just a kind of a
biological self truth and he went yeah
and and you kind of see that because
there are not many animals that kill
themselves right like there there does
seem to be some underlying pressure or
some self- evidencing survival in a way
like survival is self- evidencing but it
does bring to mind this really
interesting fact that there are some
animals who will self imilate um and I
yeah I think that is so interesting
um is there is there any kind of idea
about Beyond you know you we mentioned
ants and termites and I think that's
kind of altruism for the group um are
there any other examples that well I'm
wondering if there's any examples that
might just F be very tricky to explain
under a kind of Basia mechanics or under
an act of inference I mean and we can
expand that question more broadly and
just say is there any an Collective
behavior that you just find staggeringly
odd under like an embed markof blanket
system yeah I mean I I think like so one
of the the main reasons I went into the
collective Motion in particular like the
schooling fish and the and kind of
flocking birds was because I found them
to be exactly those examples that
violate the kind of classic image we
have of marov blankets where you have
like kind of layers of states that are
not really changing like you have the
particles on the edge of the blanket and
then you have the ones that are a little
more inside and then finally you have
the kind of hard nucleus of States yeah
um so I find that even like basic
Collective motion um kind of evades uh
proper understanding under the current
iterations of basy mechanics I mean this
is part of the reason the paper you
mentioned that kind of studies uh like
frames individual elements of like a
school as like active inference agents
that that paper actually didn't try to
formulate the whole school as a
collective that was one of the other
objectives I had during my PhD and it's
something I'd still like to to study if
I have time but um I found that actually
doing proper basing mechanics on the
whole school as if the school is the
unit of analysis was quite difficult
precisely because Collective motion is
an example where the roles that
individuals play um is changing
dynamically so if we are to find like a
stable marov blanket description that
satisfies all the tenants of the free
energy principle we will have to kind of
come up with a more Dynamic um version
of system identification that allows you
to kind of uh dynamically redraw who is
a sensory State what parts of your
high-dimensional state space are playing
the role of active versus sensory versus
internal dynamically over time so I
think even like the most kind of basic
examples ant Colones as well right
they're Dynamic mixing system although
the roles are more genetically
predetermined for social
insects all these examples I think are
are a bit of a challenge to the classic
formulation of basy mechanics um right
well I guess one of the earlier
critiques of active inference was that
it's a kind of state based um Sy you
know formalism which doesn't allow for
kind of dynamic change as you say and
over ESS and I recognize I think this is
something that actually came up in a odd
Twitter discussion between Maxwell and
Kate Nave about um path integrals and
the path Dynamics it might be you know
you're right at the Forefront of This
research maybe it's worth just for the
audience
unpicking what is the difference between
a kind of state based or static active
inference versus a path-based active
inference which allows for this kind of
well I you know think of
metamorphosizing Mark of blankets or
something like that yeah yeah for sure
so the the classic um variant of
deriving the free energy principle rests
on specifying like a what's called a
steady St distribution so it's actually
just a probability distribution over the
states of the system that should not
change um and this is you know this can
generally be applied to many systems at
least on some time scale like so it
seems like the distribution of particles
in a rock or me and you for example
doesn't seem to change on quite so long
of a time scale of course the rub is in
how do I Define what a state is is a
state of particular cell because cells
are turning over all the time or is it
maybe tissue things like that but anyway
the the basic um free energy Principle
as it was I mean I I guess as it was
pedagogically described this is I'm
referring to papers like the free energy
principle for a particular physics the
monograph from
2019 so the idea is you you have this
stationary distribution Over States and
and it's a like very trivially a
multivariate system so there's a
potential for some of those states to be
active States sensory States internal
States you've kind of partition the
system but what's important is that over
a long times if I measure the system the
probability distribution of being in
this part of State space or this part of
State space that probability is fixed it
doesn't change over time so it still
allows for particles to move around if I
look at the individual trajectories like
things can change there can be
fluctuations but the stationary density
the probabilities are are constant yeah
that's in contrast with the more recent
path integral or path form
where it's not the distribution over um
the states themselves like finding my
position in this part of the room at
over time on average but it's more a
probability distribution over paths or
trajectories themselves so the point of
this is that um there's also a
stationary measure or a stationary
distribution but it's not over
particular points in state space but
it's rather over sequences of points Y
and that allows you to have a lot more
flexibility in the Dynamics where you
can have things that appear
non-stationary in the sense of if I look
at just the positions of the variables
that will be changing over time but it's
because there's actually a more like
abstract stationary measure which is
operating on the paths or the sequences
of variables of the system um so yeah
this is what
allows I mean apparently this is I think
what's going to be upcoming as we see
this formulation unpacked more
especially in terms of simulations we're
going to see versions of this basing
mechanics applied to systems that are
moving in time and not stationary and
this is only something you can get with
the path-based
formulation so when you talk about the
states uh so we're either talking about
the source of path that states take or
the kind of position that they have at a
given time what part of the mark of
blanket are we talking here because some
people talk about the internal States uh
you know parametrizing beliefs over
external states and they self-
evidencing and then some people talk
about the actual blanket States or the
par or some people blanket States
reducing VF or so people talk about the
particular states which is the blanket
States plus the internal States so when
we're talking about
States uh tending towards an attracting
set what what what what are the
commitments that we're making here in
terms of which states those are so yeah
people will disagree on this I mean in
the original formulation of the free
energy principle it should be all of
those things yeah so blanket sensory
active and internal all have a
stationary distribution defined over
them right so so it's basically the
joint distribution of all the subsets of
States that's the thing that should be
unchanging is that including would that
include the external States or we're
allowing those to have
some non you know chaotic element to
them yeah I mean for the mathematics in
the original formulation to work you
actually also need the external states
to be unchanging which is one of the
critiques that the enry principle had
got is like you're not really defining a
stationary system to be the system per
se like the agent but you're actually
including the whole world yeah yeah
agent is embedded in as part of your
stationary measure and you know you
could make arguments that oh well it's
um you know referring to just the Eco
Niche like the behaviorally relevant
part of the agent's world that it's
trying to control so it's kind of like
the agent is forcing its external states
to to obey the stationary measure um but
I think the path-based for foration
allows you to get around that because
all these things now become
nonstationary if considered in terms of
just raw States but but yeah it
originally it does include all all the
subsets of States but it sounds like
even when we're talking about the change
of uh the path of states there still
seems to be some kind of predetermined
characteristics or predetermined
attracting set such that path is tending
towards a certain probability for sure
so you're allow for some what Carl would
call sort of itinerancy or you know some
deviation from that ideal but you still
got some pre- caracteristic uh Dynamics
I'm just wondering you know you'll know
a lot more about physics than I do how
much does that really square with kind
of fundamental physics or our
understanding of the world like is it is
it actually feasible to say even if we
allow for some itinerancy and change
over time there are there's like a
mathematical way that you could still
describe that yeah I I think it that
actually that assumption is quite
consistent with physics because I mean
there there's a lot of like uh
equivalency between these different
things so as soon as I say oh these
stochastic differential equations tend
toward some attracting
set another way of saying that is I've
just written down a particular form of
their flow like the way that they change
over time some particular equations of
motion yeah and if those equations of
motion meet a few basic constraints like
one of them is that they don't diverge
infinite into positive or negative
Infinity which is like I think a a
pretty safe assumption I mean if we if
we're assuming all of our equations
diverges to Infinity we wouldn't be able
to do much with them so as long as you
say that this equation doesn't diverge
to Infinity another way of saying that
is there is some measure that this
belongs to it basically will tend
towards something with constant
probabilities and those constant
probabilities in in certain systems will
be better um described in terms of paths
rather than States so like the paths of
the system will have constant
probability so although that sounds like
restricting it's actually it's actually
just a statement of writing down any
differential equation that doesn't have
some crazy like kind of impossible form
right yeah okay final question on the
physics uh because you did a reply to
this how particular is the physics of
the free energy principle Pap by aguera
and colleagues and I just was really
curious because it it's very much
pertains to what I was saying about what
states are we talking about the
particular States the internal States
the blanket States and you say in that
paper and I can quote I express General
agreement with the target article
statement that the marginal flow of
internal states does not point along
variational free energy gradients
evaluated the most likely internal State
however in this commentary I focus on
the flow of particular States intern
brackets internal and blanket states and
their variational free energy gradients
and the average flow of these systems do
point along variational free energy
gradients and in my notes I've literally
just written what does this
mean yeah no thanks for bringing that up
because that I I wrote another
commentary I think on the same article
that was a lot more like it was more
about this sparse coupling conjecture
and that one actually didn't get much
attention but so yeah that
effectively this is a very interesting
point because the the one of the main
hypotheses of the free energy principle
and this manifests in terms of like
particular process theories like
predictive coding is that if you look at
the internal states of some system
they're pointing directly towards the
free energy minimum so either on average
or if it's deterministic for a
particular path the system looks like
it's minimizing free energy very nicely
so in the same way we train deep neural
networks to exactly maximize the ability
to predict the test data we train
predictive coding networks to exactly
minimize free energy so they're taking
like the direction of steepest descent
towards the free energy minimum and at
that minimum is where your inference is
best you're at the local minimum of the
free energy your inference over external
States is the best it can be given your
approximate exterior in your generative
model so what Agera at all's um paper
found is that if you look at like very
simple stochastic differential equations
these are like uh in this class of
linear system so they're very easy to
analy and they're probably not the best
model of the more complex systems we're
actually interested in in biology but
they're a really good starting point
what they found is that sorry
sorry got to walk
um uh that they found that even for
these simple linear systems the average
internal states are actually not
pointing towards these free energy
minimum and that was kind of posed as
like a challenge to the free energy
principle and the the mathematics behind
that derivation in my opinion were uh
totally sound so it is true that
actually even in these uh very simple
linear diffusion systems you don't get
this kind of nice interpretation as
internal States walking in the steepest
direction towards the best inference
they're actually taking a more
circuitous route towards the minimum
which entails the best inference however
if you extend your um your kind of your
your definition of internal states to
include also the active States and the
sensory States so the part so-called
particular States the things that
differentiate the particle from the
external environment then those things
actually are pointing down free energy
gradients and this kind of is in line
with this
general idea that I think is a lot more
in line with like the idea of sensory
motor coupling it's not just the
internal states that are doing inference
but the internal states are kind of
cooperating or conspiring with your
active States in order to
collaboratively get to that free energy
minimum at which point inference is
exact or as exact as it can be given
your approximations so it's saying okay
I don't need to go the the steepest way
to the free energy minimum I can take
like a kind of curvy circuitous route
but I'm at the same time I'm pushing my
active and sensory States in such a way
that will actually minimize the time it
takes us to get to the free energy
minimum and that was kind of the point
of that um of that article or one of the
points no that's really useful I'm just
wondering um so when we talk about
so we're talking here about the sort of
self- evidencing or the gradient Descent
of particular States um should we is
could we say that actually it might what
would it make okay what would it mean to
say what would it mean what would it
look like if I said we're doing gradient
descent just on blanket States so let's
just ignore Silo off the internal States
for a second and just say are blanket
States absent the internal States also
do they Al Point down variational free
energy gradients yeah I don't think that
is guaranteed actually I don't think
blanket states are are necessarily
pointing down um free energy gradients
necessarily without taking into account
sensory and uh or sorry uh internal
States so the internal states are kind
of the things that are driving the
active states to jointly minimize the
free energy and the free energy recall
is defined on both the blanket and the
internal States because it's defined on
the observation which are like the
blanket States and it's also defined on
your beliefs over external states which
in this case are parameterized by
internal States so if you define the the
free energy just on the blanket States I
don't think it's guaranteed to it will
be minimized in the long run but it's
not guaranteed that the Dynamics are
pointing in the direction of steepest
descent how do you when people so I
think people this is kind of coming to
the kind of education of Act of
influence I guess and and part of this
podcast is me learning and the audience
learning alongside with me when people
when people like you talk about internal
States I understand what it means to
sort of parameterize ex uh beliefs over
external States and in some ways you're
doing vfe because you want to return to
like a set of external states which is
viable for your existence so fish are
not going to be found outside water or
I'm not going to be found in an ice cube
so on Ice Cube freezer I don't know um
now my sort of persistent question I've
always had and I don't think anyone has
really answered and I'm not sure there
is an answer is is that we say that the
internal states are kind of the vehicle
for these beliefs but are they could you
also just say they are these beliefs
like is there anything over and above
the internal States Beyond these basian
beliefs yeah no that's a really good
question so this is this this gets into
a bigger question also about
identifiability and uniqueness of the
free energy principle and basy mechanic
so Bas in short the the internal states
are not just simply the beliefs because
they are whatever physically they are
like if if we're looking at a school of
fish and we're saying these five fish
are playing the role of the internal
States or looking at a cell this part of
DNA is is playing the role of the
internal States it's coding the the um
production of proteins that itself that
internal State doesn't have anything
intrinsically it's not parameterizing
parameters of probability distributions
over external States so what's
always at play when you're saying that
the internal states are about or some in
somehow representing external States is
there's always a function there which in
the classic free energy literature is
called the synchronization map and what
this is is it's a function that takes
your internal States and it Maps them
into the parameters of probability
distributions so if I want it's
basically something that takes the raw
like dirty physics of the system however
it is it's like you know the metals and
the ions and the the the things that
actually consist of your system and it's
mapping them into a space of probability
distribution so if we wanted to say that
um my neurons are encoding beliefs about
the position of objects in the room what
that that function that synchronization
map would be doing is it would like take
the firing rate of a neuron which is
like an actual physical
neurophysiological property that I can
measure from the neuron and it's mapping
it to something like the mean of a gaan
distribution or the variance of a
gaussian distribution so I mean I guess
in that sense it's
like do you think that the firing rates
of the neuron simply are the belief I
would say that and actually this this
kind of hints at at something I I um saw
you talking about Alex kefir on on one
of your earlier podcasts is like this
kind of identity problem like are the
neural firing rates the belief the
representation themselves or is there
some map that takes the physics of the
system and then Maps it into a
probability distribution into a
representation so I think you always do
need that function that actually takes
the system and Maps it to a belief but
the problem with identifiability is it
seems like there may be many candidate
functions that take this the system
States and map them to a probability
distribution over beliefs so it's very
hard to just look at a system and say oh
yeah it's forming beliefs about like the
average distance to neighbors or the the
light refraction in the room or the
contrast of some some image out there we
we usually come to the table with very
strong priors about for instance neural
coding we think that neurons either code
things with the timing of spikes or they
use like the firing rate and that's how
they do the encoding and that's
basically saying we come to the table
with priors about what that function is
but in theory there's nothing about the
free energy principle that tells you
what that function is so it's a very
hard like identifiability problem in
general
okay that's interesting yeah I mean
another thing that kind of sticks in my
mind when I think about this
is where does the where do like where do
the beliefs stop so what point is
something internal to the system and
what point is something external to the
system so um like for example let's say
my I right there's something like me
let's take as a kind of presupposition I
am conducting variational basan
inference like over the external States
but the external States in some strange
way are also myself right because
they're also let's say the observations
that come with respect to my glucose
levels now that's because I need to have
some beliefs right some probability
distribution that my glucose levels are
going to tend towards a certain point in
that like there is some internal belief
about an external state but that
external state is actually still within
me I we get we kind of get around this
through this notion of embedded Marco
blankets right like I'm not actually
parametrizing those beliefs but actually
my CES are but I guess the point here is
is it we it comes back to a question
that I've had loads of times and people
have had different answers to it is this
just a useful structuring tool here
where I can just say well I don't really
know why or how or when this Mark of
blanket ends and becomes part of a
bigger order Mark of blanket and so on
until you get something that it's like
to be me but it's useful and we can do
useful maths or useful physics based on
it because I just think like again it's
philosophically vague as to does it make
like is the cell is it part of the you
know is there just a straight allision
really between an internal State and an
external state from the perspective of a
cell because it seems that it's also
doing basian beliefs on its own location
its own status its own right like so
I've always struggled with that with the
free energy principle yet it makes sense
for me that the internal States I have
to parameterizing beliefs about where I
am in the world or who I'm with and so
on but what about like what about myself
I've got to be about my glucose levels
my temperature my well-being and all the
way down to my like very granular
physics level yeah where does it stop
yeah exactly I I think the generic
answer to this I think is basically what
you meant by embedded Markov blankets
which is if I if I look at like a coar
grain level like more a psychological
level of explanation like you you have
beliefs about who's in the other room or
what's behind your door so that itself
could be drawn out as like a basian
network where you have some sensory
states which are like your sensory
organs like your eyes and ears and nose
and then you have your internal state
which is like your psychological state
or something or some coar grin
representation of what your brain is
thinking and then you have that external
state which is like the presence or
absence of another person each of those
nodes in our basing graph we can kind of
double click on and like zoom in and
that itself is a a a a thing that has
internal blanket sensory so that's like
the generic answer that that um people
like Carl frisen will talk about with
the renormalization group like you have
marov blankets at different scales and
of course the work of Maxwell ramstead
and people like that who are literally
like writing papers about how exactly
this happens you have this nested markup
blanket so I think that is the the
general answer is that every time we
write down a basian Network and a graph
we're like saying okay that's the
blankets that's the internal that's the
external every time we do that we're
kind of admitting well actually I can
always like take what I consider a
single state and just rip it up and like
start partitioning that right and then I
think the the ultimate conclusion of
that exercise is basically your
conclusion which is it all becomes a
matter of why are we doing this like why
am why am I at this level of zoomed
outness and is probably for some
practical utility as a modeler as a
neuroscientist as a
physicist yeah yeah so if we take the
sort of
psychological perspective and let's say
you know so let's say you actually will
use your uh preprint so the paper that I
was mentioning before was from the um I
believe it's Collective behavior from
surprise minimization so that's a really
great preprint that people can check out
is obviously quite technical but there's
again lots of things that people can get
out of it um let's say you know we embed
these we're doing these um basian belief
over the distance that I am from another
person and the rate of change of that
distance I guess my question here is am
I also conducting basing beliefs about
where I am do I get where I am out of
just like do I get where I am just out
of the beliefs about where other people
are even at very psychological level you
know there's someone else in the other
room do I also need to be
doing basian beliefs about myself in
relation to those external world and
does that mean that I am also in some
ways like I've got a jeel perspective
I've got like this jeal monism where I
am doing the basian belief about myself
as if I was part of exteral world yeah
kind of like doing doing theory of mind
on your own self having to simulate your
own inference process yeah I mean so I
think the argument made in that
Collective behavior from Surprise
minimization paper is that um you can
get away without that very like you can
get away with a lot of coordinated
Behavior
where agents are tuning their own
position and their velocity and space
just by operating on very low-level
reflex arcs basically just trying to
minimize sensory prediction error and so
those agents in that paper don't have
any representation of their own position
that's not like a latent variable in
their generative model all they do is
they have some velocity vector and that
induces prediction errors and what they
can do is they can just change that
velocity to basically reduce prediction
errors so you can get a get quite a lot
of sophisticated Behavior without that
representation however I think there are
plenty of good examples of systems and
maybe this gets more into like what you
would call metacognition although it
doesn't even have to be
that but there are systems where you
would like to have a representation of a
random variable in your system that
represents something like the self
position y um and and you would like to
do inference over that variable and that
basically is what active inferences if I
have a a variable that corresponds to
some latent that can control my own body
position or my speech or whatever and
doing inference over that latent
variable is basically what ends up being
some kind of agency or control and I
think the Reas the cases when you would
want to have that extra variable are
ones where the Dynamics of yourself are
are above and beyond what can just be
determined from your sensory inputs so
for like these reflexive fish I can get
away without having a self variable
because their behavior is pretty much
completely a deterministic function of
their sensory states there is a little
bit of like memory in there because they
have the belief from the last time step
of belief updating but it's very simple
it's not like a very complex dependency
when you have individual um agents that
have a lot of like autonomy I guess
which I would just parse into like more
long-term nonlinear Dynamics then it
makes sense to introduce another latent
variable in your model that corresponds
to something like myself or my position
or my actions and at that point you're
going to get more of like a I would say
a tension between externally driven um
behaviors that are driven by sensory
stimul only and internal more like
endogenous or autonomous behaviors and
that's that those are the cases when you
would want to put that latent variable
in there yeah I've been I've been
thinking about this myself we're just
finishing up these edits for this flow
States paper and um trying to explain
sort of with lar and Carl and and others
and trying to explain sort of what it
means for the you know this the self is
the so-called s hid like one of just
many hidden causes according to act of
inference is hypothesis cause and trying
to explain kind of the difference
between an internal cause and an
external cause for something that's
already presumably internal right like
me and um yeah totally this is cool
though it's uh yeah I I think I remember
hearing may you you're probably more up
to date with this but I remember hearing
Carl talk about like the idea that the
the very fact that we introduced
something like a self was basically a
new structure in a generative model um
in order to explain disparate input so
it's like I'm hearing a bunch of speech
signals and if I don't if I only have
one latent variable in my model which is
like there is somebody speaking right
then it's not going to be a good enough
model of like the speech signals and
when you get enough of these like social
signals it actually becomes the free
energy minimizing solution to break that
node into two and there's one that I can
control and there's one that's someone
else that I can't control and that's the
best way to like explain the data well
yeah and presumably this is happening
actually in developmental psychology and
developmental biology whereby a child
doesn't really know have a self other
distinction and I I always relate this
back to I think action is very important
so this is going back to the work of
someone like Chris fiff and uh the
comparator model whereby I can make
predictions about the consequences of my
action and the Very fact that I can do
that and witness the sensory outcomes of
my action means I kind of get well I get
this sensory motor Arc and therefore I
can have a higher order inference that
there is something that that internal to
my generative model that is driving that
action I guess the question here is
what's happening in something like a
Psychopathology like for insertion in
schizophrenia where people don't trust
that the thoughts that I mean I think
this is actually kind of true and I
think the Buddhists actually flesh this
out quite well that obviously if you
actually meditate you'll see that well
the thoughts are not yours like they're
not cut they're not you're not making
the thoughts but there's a classic thing
in schizophrenia of like people who are
schizophrenia will often think that the
thoughts that they're thinking aren't
theirs they're being beamed in by an
alien or a government surveillance
operation and how you feed in something
like a predictive model into that unless
you take f as an action and then say
well I'm predicting the outcomes of my
thought and so on that becomes tricky
because I guess we think of predictions
as thoughts in some realist way and so
you end up with this circular Loop but
yeah it's um I think it's yeah it is
fascinating I think it's a I think it's
a I think this idea of the self as an
inferred cause is reasonable I think the
only problem is is that it engender some
kind of H potential
homunculus which is sort what's doing
the inference in the first place yeah
exactly um but these are these are
questions for yeah that brings you back
to having to Define internal States like
what the internal States or the self and
you're inferring that that's even exists
you need to define the inference process
on some other subset of States like
that's get ground in the first place
yeah exactly yeah cool uh well you've
just given me another paper idea and
maybe a PhD idea um so okay awesome I
wanted to ask about this scene
construction paper because I've been
really interested in scene construction
and I was I was happy you know I I saw
you work with bet mitzer and I think his
work is really amazing
uh and I just wrote his paper on
attention and it's super inspired by
what he was doing with Carl and this
especially their selective attention
paper the 2019 paper yeah definitely
yeah maybe just for the audience who
aren't who probably have a idea and
intuition what scene construction is and
they probably think of it as visual
although I really like the sort of
language example here maybe yeah you
could explain just very s of high level
what scene construction is yeah no I
like that you brought up the language
example because that that's actually
what originally compelled me even when I
saw those papers on scene construction I
actually immediately thought of it in
terms of like parsing and language a
scene construction is just kind of a a
type of hidden variable inference so I
have a bunch of sparsely sampled data
points and then given that sequence of
data points like little sensory samples
I suddenly kind of infer something
that's explaining all of them at once
like oh this this is the latent cause
this is the latent exp explanation that
kind of unifies all these disperate um
these disperate data points and I guess
the construction aspect comes from two
ways one is the fact that usually the
way we get that sequence of sparse data
is through some kind of sampling so like
as I read a sentence I I'm typ in in
like Western languages you're typically
reading left to right as my eyes go
right across the page I'm gathering more
evidence and I'm constructing the scene
as in my posterior probability
distribution over these different
explanations is kind of shifting until
at some point and often we see with
human language and visual understanding
there's kind of this like nonlinear
feedback where oh it it kind of snaps
into place oh this is what's going on
and it's very interesting seeing this in
language too like in different languages
like German for instance the verb will
come at the end of the sentence so you
kind of have to wait until the end of
the sentence before that meaning kind of
snaps into place so that that's
generally what I would describe as scene
construction and then in the visual case
often it's um you might be looking at a
a uh a painting or something like an
ambiguous painting let's say some a
modernist maybe abstract thing with not
very clear figures and you're sparsely
sampling it with your eyes trying to
figure out like what what's actually
going on here and at some point when
sampling you you get that just stal
impression of oh there's like a a figure
in a cloak or something and that that
moment of gal recognition is like the
the act of constructing the scene of
inferring the latent explan for all the
sensory data that I've that I've
gathered excellent that's really useful
I guess something that Beck's work
really drove home to me and impelled me
to write this paper was the importance
of context so if you're doing a sort of
Yus task um where you have a PCT exactly
what you just said you have a picture
and then someone says well how rich are
the family in this picture and then you
scan all of the furniture and you look
at their clothes and then they they are
something else like I don't know I I
don't actually know what it is but you
know let's say how well do they get
along with each other and you look at
how they're sitting and you look at whe
they're looking at each other so context
is clearly driving a kind of
overall uh the the the kind of
derivation of a latent C in some ways
because you're going okay well I'm going
to pick out this evidence and that's
going to drive my inference so are we
would you say that we're always
integrating a kind of higher order
context when we're doing scene
construction such that you know there is
no such thing as the kind of neutral
scene um it's always you know the
inference is always being driven by our
recognition of where we are what we are
and so on totally yeah I think that's
that that's one of the most interesting
aspects of basian modeling in general is
like the the the ability for people to
very rapidly infer a context which in in
to map it back to the the kind of
abstraction I used to describe scene
Construction in the beginning is like
you're inferring which latent
explanation
you're even testing yeah exactly the cas
of um you get the sense that the family
in in the painting is Rich you're
suddenly that's inference of a rapid
context that then induces which latent
explanations am I interested in learning
about right like Rich versus not rich
whereas if it if the um the cue or the
prompt was is the man wearing a red
shirt then the different latent
explanations that you've suddenly
inferred you have to test is a different
set yeah I think that's like one of the
most amazing and and kind of
underexplored
abilities that humans and other animals
have is they can in they can use context
to basically quickly infer a generative
model so like the context kind of
selects the generative model that then
you use to do something like active
inference Yeah well yeah I've been
thinking about this um because clearly
clearly it's it's just not
computationally feasible to uh
contemplate or assess every possible
State I mean this is the
basis of variational basing inference is
that kind of P of Y is just it's in
almost infinitely diverse in its state
space and so I've been kind of proposing
that there's a higher order action
policy which does the kind of pruning um
to use reinforcement language the kind
of pruning of your potential State space
and i' be thinking about that a lot in
terms of action because even action like
you can't I don't consider doing
absolutely everything at any given time
have you got any other like fur
intuitions about how that might work
because I think the slight the slight
tricky thing here is that we have a kind
of higher order policy let's say to
prune our state space but that needs
itself to be driven by
observation right I need to know okay
I'm going to prune accordingly because
I've observed something in the world
right like so I see that it's raining
for example in London right now and so
like I'm just immediately pruning
swimming trunks and sunglasses and so on
but I needed to do that observation in
the first place so it sounds like I got
have to hire order the action policy to
observe the world to drive my context
I'm just curious about how much how How
Deeply recursive does that go yeah I I
think like the the
overall my I mean I would like to think
that there's a generic solution where
you basically can start with no
structure and like build everything from
scratch but I think there's basically no
free lunch here even and I agree with
you that like maybe the best way to
explain human behavior is that you're
inferring a or inferring um something
that then allows you to prune or select
a model that then you can use in
practice but the process by which you do
that also assumes some kind of model
like what's the model by which you infer
I need to act to do this where those
models come from these like deep hyper
priors about the spaces of models that I
can select at at like a lower level
those are probably things that are
developmentally inborn those are that's
probably the space that like Evolution
actually works on like on the space of
kind of hyper priors or deep hyper
models that like babies are born within
their brain and these things are are
probably things that you and I couldn't
elucidate in like like in in human
cognitive neurosciences like a
probability of the dots moving right
versus left like that's a likelihood we
can write down these kinds of models
that are like the models about how do I
select which structures to use for a
given task those are probably very hard
to put into words but those are the
sorts of things that I expect
developmental psychologists have
somewhat of a hold on like these they
probably have to do with like intuitive
folk physics like things like there
there are objects there are agents there
are things with like spacio temporal
correlations over time like very deep
physical constructs but um but I do I do
think that at a More mechanistic Level
what you're saying makes a lot of sense
I I think like one way you could
formulate this is in terms of mixture
models so mixture models is like I have
some assignment variable that's very
high up that tells me which model am I
using right now and so the mixing
variable is what you infer and then
given the inference of the mixing
variable that effectively selects one of
five or 10 or a thousand different
alternative explanations for the data
and usually those are form are are
models of the same form like a gaussian
mixture model is a mixture of gaussians
but I think in what you're discussing
what you're mixing are like totally
alternative structures
like one structure that I'm inferring
one context I'm inferring I'm in is like
I'm driving a race car another context
is that I'm talking to a friend or a
colleague and those are totally
different models um I think one place
where the mixture model falls apart is
with mixture models you would assume
that when you infer that higher level
assignment sometimes that inference can
kind of be wide so you're not sure what
context you're in but when you look at
human behavior people tend not to mix
context there's some experimental
paradigms where you get that but often
people infer like they kind of Select
like I'm definitely going to make these
assumptions going forward I'm definitely
going to make these so there might be
something like a better model of
structure selection than mixture models
but that would be one idea I think like
mathematically where to get started
would to be looking at like mixtures of
structures effectively yeah yeah yeah
nice I I spoke to sanjie now Joshi about
this on the podcast who's versus with
you and yesterday I spoke to him about
it and we went back and forth and I
think we ended up grounding out in
evolution so I think you're absolutely
you're absolutely right I think yeah
there are a couple of things I want to
say to that one is it's always I tell
everyone this on this podcast and
personally that I think it's always a
bit dangerous to just take one slice of
the generative model at one slice of
time and take that to be what's actually
happening it's always Dynamic your
observations are always feeding into the
upper levels which are feeding back down
I guess that's the beauty of a kind of
predictive coding or a deep parametric
modeling system is that like this is
just an idealization it's it's it's
constantly
happenings um I think the other like
point of uh complexity here is that not
only uh do we need to let's say derive a
context we also have to derive the
salience of a context or like the
relevance of a context so you know I've
been yeah I wrote this paper where I'm
kind of talking about the circular
causality between preferences and
attention and something that I kind of
realized was well and well I knew it
obviously because it's just for my life
that if I'm hungry like if I'm truly
starving I'm not I don't care about
anything else that's on like that seems
fundamentally peripheral at that time
whether that's finishing a paper or you
know being on my phone and so on which
means that like there's almost not only
is there a higher order policy that I
prune my state space according to the
fact that I'm now hungry but also that
now trumps any other state possible
State space like I'm on my phone or I'm
riding my S
which implies that there's like an even
higher level Precision waiting policy
that says well not only do you have to
prune accordingly but you also have to
prune in a hierarchical fashion yeah and
I don't know again I don't know how deep
this goes because as Carl will tell us
anatomically the brain is very ridy and
very
recursive yeah that's true no that I
mean that also reminds me I think of
this paper of Burks that you mentioned
from 2019 right because if I remember
correctly that version of selective
attention depended on the preferences is
that right so yeah that that's something
like other than other than that work by
Burke and I guess the paper you're
discussing now I don't know of much work
that explicitly uses the preferences to
then select what generative model is
being used for inference because you're
absolutely right it's not just oh I have
some observations then I infer the
context which then tells me how to act
but that inference also depends on like
what your goals are like what is
important right now and usually we get
importance in the kind of classic
modelbased reinforcement learning way is
we we roll out a given policy and we see
how much does that policy overlap with
what I want like a reward function you
basically evaluate policies in terms of
reward functions but what you're
suggesting maybe cannot be accommodated
in that way where the actual inference
itself is biased by it's not just policy
selection but even State selection or
state inference is biased by what's
important what's relevant um and I think
you there are ways you can get that like
there's this um generalized free energy
paper by Thomas par and Carl frisen from
2019 where they show that in that in
that particular formulation of
variational free energy called the
generalized free energy you actually do
get this interesting influence on state
inference from preferences so your
preferences will kind of optimistically
bias your state inference so that you'll
only be doing inference about things
that kind of matter for your action
selection so that might be one one place
to
card pointed me in the direction of that
paper because he read it he read my
paper and then obviously didn't tell me
about this one that sounds absolutely
right yeah because I mean my way of
coming at it was thinking
well in principle you know there's near
infinite things that I can optimize my
free energy minimization over right like
I and there are ways out of this I mean
some people will talk about something
like uh you know Julian Kine or Mark
Miller or Mark Anderson was about
aerodynamics so it's not enough just to
minimize free energy that needs to be a
constantly improving slope of prediction
error
minimization but I still don't think
that does it because in principle uh I
could just get way better at tidying my
room but like that's just or or
something extremely trivial yeah that's
going to cut it ultimately because I
might just end up starving
so it's yeah is exactly as you said um I
I still think this can be couched in
terms of something like an expected free
energy function it's just it's just far
it's just higher order and everything
trickles down from it such that as you
say like now we have like a selected
generative model in truth I haven't
thought too much about how this could be
implemented mathematically because yeah
you know that's the place that that
because that is yeah that's totally true
you could actually say because because
the typical way we do the expected free
energy is in like this Brute Force
enumeration like let's say I did this I
did X versus y if I did x what would my
expected free energy look like it would
be combination of the utility which is
like the preferences and then this info
Information Gain if you were to evaluate
that Brute Force for like model
selection like if I was to select this
model and then go through a whole round
of active inflence with this model it
just becomes very hard to compute the
expected free energy I think so maybe
there's just a better algorithm or
implementation that would allow you to
kind of
heris evaluate these counterfactual
consequences of like if I selected this
model what would my would that make me
less hungry would that like Sate me um
but you probably have to come up with
some huris or some clever way to to get
around the enumeration well I wonder
whether it could just be belief free
whether you might just like we might
just have contextually cued model
selection that you know the moment that
I have the slight you know the slightest
drop in my glucose then the whole thing
Cascades down such that I have the
prioritization of seeking food and I I
don't even have to run the expected free
energy of
I could go here I could go there I could
go and and what am I you know how well
am I going to do yeah rather I just have
this one now I just at the very bottom
of all that process I just have this one
preference which is eat and I think you
know something like that might uh hijack
or or shortcut the whole process leading
to like quite low compute but actually a
pretty robust um way of like getting
adaptation because presumably this is
something similar to what a child is
doing right like yeah and and I think
that kind of works in terms of like I
don't know like the Simplicity of
children in some way is that they they
sort of cry over anything which kind of
implies that there is just like a very
simple stimulus response mapping and I
wonder whether that could just be
expanded you know just more broadly to
model selection absolutely yeah I think
that ultimately is probably what's
really happening in biology because this
is this also extends across the the bi
ological um Spectrum like animals are
very context or like basically need
driven like things like attention all
these basic cognitive faculties are
really enslaved
to effectively the basic things that the
the the lower brain is telling the body
it needs to do like breathing eating um
thirst sleeping so I think ultimately it
is some fast stimulus response mapping I
think the only issue with that is it
does kind of it it it seems less princip
right it seems like oh we just have to
hack in a short circuit and it's not
it's not just like evolving through a
neat process of free energy minimization
maybe it is but it's just happening on a
slower time scale right like it's some
slow accumulation of experience
evolutionarily that has trained this
short circuit inference to say I'm
hungry yeah there might have been some
EF calculation on the part of evolution
to select for yeah you know uh stimulus
response mappings for something very
like fundamental like food or sleep or
breathing and so on yeah exactly yeah
okay cool well that that's given me lots
of ideas I need to think about um nice
Yeah final sort of topic I want to touch
on is you know just before we went live
we spoke a little bit about you being at
versus uh full time and I I I wanted to
sort of ask again I know between the
sanjie and others that everything is
very under the wraps and I and I respect
that and I don't want Maxwell to come
and you know shake me um but so I was
curious just at a very sort of high
level you've you've gone from biology so
thinking about biological feasibility to
modeling and artificial intelligence and
trying to ground something in you know
trying to take biotic cognition and say
well what makes that intelligent and
then can we replicate that in silico or
you know in a robot I was just wondering
how biologically feasible are certain
assumptions made by active inference
modelers for example active modelers
talk about um this again not exactly my
but a mean field approximation for
example where presumably you know the
the hidden States or the different
tenses have conditional
Independence how you can take that one
you can take any other just any other
assumptions more broadly you know does
this seem to you actually biologically
feasible or is it just like an
interesting modeling tool no yeah I it's
actually those are those those are
probably the most interesting and
important examples of the assumptions we
make so I think the biggest one in one
word is
factorization the the models both the
generative model that animals have as
well as their um Q their approximate
posterior which they optimize using free
energy minimization those almost
necessarily have to be simplified in my
opinion there's some people who believe
that the brain is doing like sampling
based inference in which case they can
actually be doing full posteriors in
which they don't need any
simplifications in their model of the
world they're doing full posterior
inference on their model model I don't
think that really holds up because it's
it's way too slow to be um useful for
for the time scale that biology needs to
work on so I think those assumptions
like factorization in the generative
model those are quite realistic and
factorization in the posterior in this
approximate posterior I think that's
actually one of the coolest things about
variational inference is it seems like
something that brains can do because
once you make these factorization
assumptions what it gives you are
updates to your beliefs that are
beautifully local like they they only
need nearby information and this is kind
of the the whole um uh rallying Cry of
people like Bert Dev um who work on
these message passing and Factor graph
schemes what's beautiful about that is
it's distributed in local and that
locality inherits from the fact that
we're making factorizations or we're
making assumptions of certain variables
in my model or in my beliefs are
independent of each other the the the
like a specific question is is the mean
field factorization appropriate that one
assumes that all the different state
factors are conditionally independent
actually just fully independent that one
I think is a is an open question and so
there's there's basically a knob we can
turn from like fully factorized where
everything's super cheap and local but
you're introducing approximation error
as soon as you start making these
assumptions your beliefs are not going
to be as good at actually explaining the
data and minimizing free energy other
side we have fully enumerated
combinatoric entangled beliefs and
explanations for the world which are
maybe the most accurate but doing
inference on them is going to be
expensive and take a long time so the
open question in my mind for
biology if we were're trying to really
map biological processes to like
variational Bas and inference is like
where on that sliding scale is biology
or our particular systems so a lot of
the work that we're trying to do at
versus is basically find good settings
of that knob like we want to figure out
what is a a setting of factorization of
complexity we can build into these
models that they're still sufficiently
expressive and um and generalizable they
generalize across context across tasks
but they're not computationally insane
like we we need to make things cheap and
we need to also we would ideally like to
make them cheap enough that we could
imagine neural wetwear implementing them
with like local computation awesome yeah
yeah that's
yes I mean I guess that is the kind of
well that's always the accuracy
complexity tradeoff right I mean it's
built into the very equations um yeah
exactly I started in my introduction by
asking about a well I mentioned in my
introduction the
parentology and actually this was
probably the first question I ever had
in when I discovered active inference
what you know a year and a bit ago which
is what what is free energy right like
is there a little sensor in the brain
that is like cued into this like again
this was me being very naive is this
like little thing and it's sensing free
energy and it's trying to get it down to
this minimum which again now I think
about it obviously implies some kind of
action policy that need you know is
descending down fore energy gradients so
but like it is a naive question but in
some ways it's useful I think because it
feeds into an intuition which
is human you know there's this long
stand there was a longstanding debate
about like what life is right I mean
like theal is there like some special
source that we put into humans that just
like means that we self-organize and I
guess this is just a perennial problem
which is well why are we doing this in
the first place right kle tells us that
if we are doing you know if we are if I
can say that you're Conor today and your
Conor tomorrow I can kind of describe
what you've done but like why you do
that is a kind of mystery and I think
some people intuitively think well you
know maybe there's adaptive sensor in
the brain which tracks like this kind of
special you know thing called free
energy which is probably not happening
let's be honest
um and it's obviously an information
theoretic term that makes things comput
you tractable from a modeling
perspective but when you're talking
about putting that into an artificial
agent the question that comes to my mind
is is there anything else that you need
to do is there a higher order prior for
example you need to put into it that
means that it actually will act to
minimize variational free energy that
actually will self organize because
there it's kind of like why does a
computer work like what I've always just
like what's the kind of fundamental
thing maybe in the case of computer or
humans it's electricity is it anything
like that you need to kind of put in
that means that it just doesn't just sit
there and it's built with these
beautiful PRI but doesn't really act in
accordance with them yeah yeah no that's
a really deep question I mean so at a
fundamental level you're I totally agree
with you that there is no secret sauce
there's no special signal as soon as
I've written down any equation of motion
that doesn't explode yeah any any
equation of motion for systems that just
generally keep existing another way of
saying that is I've written down a free
I can write the Dynamics of that system
with some free energy functional so as
designers of artificial systems we have
the luxury of not having to write down
an equation of motion
that we know if we backed out the b
mechanic of it oh look it's minimizing
Frey we can start with the free energy
so as as artificial Engineers we can say
no we're gonna actually have these
things integrate equations of motion
that minimize free energy right so
that's what we do but I but systems like
self-organizing biological systems in
the same
way on on the Savannah the draft's necks
are not getting longer to reach the
trees because they want to optimize
Fitness that's a post talk like
apparently theological description for
the Dynamics of systems and then we put
a a sauce on it a descriptive sauce
called Fitness or called natural
selection that's the exact same thing
with free energy there's just Dynamics
and then post talk we dress it up with
well these these Dynamics look like
they're actually doing approximate
basian inference and that's a cool
useful in my opinion framing in the same
way natural selection is a cool useful
framing for statistical filtering of
phenotypes over Generations but as
artificers as Builders and Engineers we
can actually we can actually write
systems that optimize Fitness we can
write an algorithm we could write a
genetic algorithm that does it
automatically kind of we can also write
an algorithm that directly surfs a
fitness landscape and in the same way we
can directly write algorithms that
minimize free energy the problem is like
we now have the bir enough proof of
having to write down a gener model and
to to figure out what the free energy
the best free energy functional for for
a given um task is I think a more like
almost like complex
systems way of Designing a system would
be to actually just like design a bunch
of particles in a vat and write and like
basically design physics like design a a
particular sandbox of physics that
emergently gives rise to agents that
minimize free energy without actually
plugging that in at the lower but that
that's hard though yeah that's the that
that's kind of where I was leaning right
like I see yeah I guess like it just BR
it bring it does bring into mind sort of
just fundamental questions of tileology
yeah uh and makes you think well why is
physics doing this in the first place um
and as you say like can we have like it
probably would be in silico can we get
these kind of particles that just do
it and is there a way that we could get
to the bottom of that rung without
invoking another axium or another
miracle or another process and maybe not
you know it's um yeah that's yeah is
you're thinking that if we did it that
way so we started by just like writing
down very simple physics of like
particles in a vat and then we we get
the maian mechanics emergent for free is
because I thought about this as well in
your thinking is that like is there an
advantage to doing it that way rather
than top down well I think I think
that's in AG in the sense that to to my
kind of eyes there's a slight difference
in between natural selection and VAR and
active inference and that's because I
think um with natural selection you get
both the principle and the
process um now there are obviously some
axioms and miracles now I'm not a I'm
not a geneticist so don't shoot you know
don't shoot the messenger but like the
basic idea obviously is that you get the
mutations and mutations are what Drive
natural selection because it leads to
kind differentiation within the pool of
genes if you take a very sort Gene
focused form of Darwin darwi natural
selection but that gives you both the
principle okay over time given mutations
you there will be optimization for
Fitness just for free because you just
get obviously you get the things that
are successful in you know the genes
that permit repr reproducing themselves
being reproduced and so on but with
variational free energy and active
inference and the free energy principle
you get a principle
what you don't necessarily get is the
process namely what KL tells you is if
things persist this is what they have to
we can describe them using these
mechanics it doesn't give
you why things persist M so that's kind
of what I mean and I do think that if
you had a kind of completely neutral
system because Okay the reason why some
of these queries come to mind is because
I think in the older papers the older
active influence papers they would very
subtly squeeze in this thing where it
would say well there's also the higher
order prior that or higher order action
policy to minimize free
energy and then that I think is a very
philosophically FR thing because then
you go well is there a higher order
policy for that policy and so on right
and evolution obviously grounds some of
this out but it makes me think
like sure it's a really lovely
scientific tool
but the power is really in the process
theories whether that's coding active
influence variational message passing PP
scheme or whatever you
want because you don't get the process
for free from the free energy principle
and I think in that there's a slight
difference with
Evolution totally yeah I I see exactly
what you mean yeah I mean I guess
one I so it depends on how you define
evolution I would potentially argue that
natural selection is even happening in
nonbi olical systems and it's just the
the process theory that provides the
equivalent of mutation is maybe slightly
different right but I guess you could
still say that well there's still a
mutation like it's it's it's
just yeah it's a change exactly I think
I I my hunch is that something like that
could also be identified for a
variational free energy minimization but
I think it would be something that maybe
would not be satisfying like Dynamics
like you need which is another way of
saying change you need some function
that Maps a state to another state and
that if you iteratively apply that
function it doesn't diverge to Infinity
yeah and I think that would be like the
kind of process theoretic equivalent of
mutation in in natural selection yeah
I'm I'm sure someone's gonna do it it
probably won't be me probably will be
Cole let's be honest
um yeah it comes back I think to this
idea that Kate was talking about in I
haven't read her book but I know it's
out which is the
maybe a slight concern with active
inference and the free energy principle
is that at its very core it rests on
some kind of determined characteristics
mhm and maybe I mean all theories have
their axioms right I mean all theories
have their miracles and natural
selection definitely has its Miracles
but it's very neat and clever and it all
wraps up quite nicely and yeah I think
you're absolutely right that maybe
there's a little bit more work to do to
really get the process of like why
things don't just fall the part I mean
this Ringer's big question right I mean
yeah and Call's big question but yeah I
think it's very important for an
audience to realize that when we talk
about Act of inference being the
overarching theory of
everything that's probably never never
really made those claims yeah I I
totally agree we we need we don't have
the physics of why things don't fall
apart yet we've assumed that that
physics works and is there and then we
do the free energy yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah and which makes one think and this
is no disrespect to Carl or you or maxw
or anyone who's deeply invested in this
like exactly how much are we getting out
of the free energy principle because I
think Carl himself takes a very
deflationary or torist count of the free
energy principle which is that it just
says if things persist they act and
perceive like things that would persist
do right like they act things act in
accordance with themselves if they are
to exist as
themselves but as I said how things do
that right you have to do that if if I
make the fundamental free competition
you are the same thing today as tomorrow
like you have to at least be obeying by
that principle how you do
that well I guess we'll never well we
might know um con this was really really
fun um no it's these are wonderful deep
questions and I'm actually just very
glad I think something that people need
to be more of is epistemically
humble um and say where they don't know
the answer and I'm very much in
admiration of the fact that you're
willing to say that there are plenty of
things that this community still doesn't
know um oh than yeah so and yeah the
insights are just wonderful I mean I my
final question actually is just a
curious curiosity which is you were a
neuroscientist right so Master's
Neuroscience PhD
Neuroscience how on Earth did you learn
all the maths and the
physics just curiosity no that's a a
great question um yeah so I I did my
bachelor's in kind of more cognitive
Neuroscience doing a lot of EEG
psycholinguistic stuff so not really
math heavy at all and then in my last
year of Bachelors I took one um
computational Neuroscience class at
University of Pennsylvania it was VJ
balas Superman and he was the teacher um
and it just really turned my mind not
only to comp neuro but then all the
methods that you need to know to do
proper computation neur size and that
kind of just opened the Pandora's Box a
little bit and then I did a two-year
internship at the National Institute on
drug abuse and we were doing again like
translational pre-clinical Neuroscience
working with rats and mice and just
during the evenings during that that
two-year stint I was taking all these
like machine learning and computational
Neuroscience classes that at the time in
like 2015 we're still like free on
corsera so like Andrew in's course Jeff
hinton's class and I yeah I just like
had to teach myself a bunch of math um
and it was annoying and hard but it I I
think it it helps me catch up a lot to a
point where I could then go and read
Carl's papers and actually like kind of
understand what's going on yeah but it
was definitely a really long and like
self-taught journey and because of that
I do have a lot of like foundational
gaps in math that people like Lance to
Costo like you can clearly tell by
talking to him he doesn't have those
gaps because he has that that proper
education well I'll tell you there's one
man with the biggest gap of them all and
that's me so um the PHD will be fun um
it'll be great yeah yeah we'll be
bootstrapping our way to some kind of
mathematical adequacy definitely
wonderful wonderful wonderful wonderful
so much to think about um so many
wonderful insights and great intuitions
and yeah it's just been an absolute
pleasure on my part and I'm sure
everyone will benefit accordingly so
thanks yeah it's been so nice thanks for
inviting me in the first place and it
was really a pleasure talking to you it
was great wonderful Connor Thank you so
so much again thank you